SUSAN NJERI MAINA

Python Developer

+254 724 793817

suemnjeri@gmail.com

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/suemnjeri
GitHub: https://github.com/suemnjeri
Medium: https://suemnjeri.medium.com/

PROFILE

Self-motivated Python developer with skills in data analysis and visualization, web development using flask, database management using SQL, and AWS cloud computing. I'm also a technical blogger on medium with over 30 articles 600,000 views. Demonstrates exceptional operational and managerial skills with over four years of experience managing people in the hospitality industry and the commercial cleaning sector.

SKILLS

Python, SQL, AWS cloud platform, Git, Github, Flask, Docker, Kubernetes, Travis CI, Pandas.

EDUCATION

Cloud Developer Nanodegree

Udacity April 2022 – August 2022

Software Development Diploma (Java and MySQL Database management)

Digital Age Institute, Nairobi Kenya (2012 – 2013)

Bachelor of Science: Food Science and Nutrition

Jomo Kenyatta University Of Agriculture And Technology (Jkuat), Thika, Kenya (2006 – 2009)

PROFESSIONAL COURSES

AWS Cloud Concept Datacamp (July 2022)

Introduction to Python Datacamp (Feb 2022)

Computer Programming Certificate (2010)

Web design certificate (2010)

ICDL Certificate (International Computer Driving Licence) (2005)

PROJECTS

Python data analysis and visualization of the Stackoverflow 2020 survey

• Utilized the python libraries Pandas, Numpy, matplotlib and seaborn to download the data from the website, analyse it, and create visualizations to answer business questions. Saved the code on Github.

Analysed the performance of my medium articles using Python

• Analysed the performance of my medium articles using pandas, matplotlib and seaborn to find the qualities of my best performing articles.

Leveraged Flask and SQLAlchemy to create a Task manager web application and deploy on heroku

• Used Python, Flask, SQLAlchemy and a virtual environment to create a task manager where you can create, delete, and update tasks.

Refactored a Monolith image-filtering application to Micro services and implemented a CI/CD pipeline using Docker, Kubernetes and Travis Ci

 Created a PostgreSQL database on AWS RDS for storing the app's metadata and an S3 bucket for the images. Configured each micro service to run in its own Docker container. Set up a Travis CI pipeline to push images to Dockerhub and deployed the Dockerhub images to a Kubernetes cluster

Deployed a 'TODO' application using AWS Lambda and Serverless framework

• Configured the serverless.yml with the backend's handler and helper functions, allocated the the necessary AWS resources such as DynamoDB and and S3 bucket in the 'resources' section, enabled distributed tracing using AWS X-Ray and configured he frontend that required login through the Auth0 portal into the app.

Hosted a static website on Amazon S3 bucket and used CloudFront service (content delivery network) to access the cached website

WORK EXPERIENCE

Business Analyst (Contract)
Faidi Properties Limited, Nairobi
March 2018 – Present

• Implemented a record-keeping system for maintaining the running accounts of tenants for a real estate company using Python, QuickBooks and Ms Excel.

Technical Blog Writer (Freelancer) Medium.com, Towards Data Science December 2020 – Present

- Researched on and wrote 25 articles about Data Science tutorials on medium.com that have over half a million views. Used Github to store the code files that support these articles.
- Sample: https://towardsdatascience.com/lambda-functions-with-practical-examples-in-python-45934f3653a8

Co-Founder and Manager Woojoo Restaurant, Nairobi August 2017 – December 2019

- Developed and maintained Excel spreadsheets for managing cash flow, accounts payable, and inventory.
- Sourced for and installed a point of sale application that doubled the service delivery and reduced pilferage.
- Worked with the team to develop operational manuals and checklists for the different departments.
- Installed and trained the staff on a point of sale system for to streamline service operations, increase efficiency, reduce pilferage, and inform better business decisions using the data collected.

Site Manager

Chania Cleaners Limited, Nairobi

Jan 2011 - Jan 2013

• Supervised and managed the cleaning operations of 4 Commercial banks (Equity banks) within Nairobi City, each with a team of five cleaners.

PASSION PROJECTS

Media Screen Projector OneTribe Church, Nairobi

2018 - Present

• Organized and projected the text and media such as songs, notices, and sermon notes to the church's screens. Planned and coordinated the volunteer roster for the media team.

Tax returns officer - VAT, NHIF, PAYE and NSSF

Acacia Traders

Oct 2021 - Present

• Performed timely monthly Tax returns for VAT, NHIF, PAYE, NSSF for the company.

ACTIVITIES

- Successful participant of the 1st Zindi Mentorship Programme in 2020.
- Graduate of the 2022 ALX-T Cloud developer cohort.